foreign
hello and welcome everyone
it is September 19th 2020-23 and we are
in octave math stream number 7.1 at the
Active inference Institute we're here
with Vincent Wang mashinitsa and guests
it should be quite a discussion
certainly a unique one by what we can
already see so thank you all for joining
we'll be looking forward to this
presentation and
interleave in discussion
thanks Dan
um so hi my name is Vincent and uh with
me today also is Hamza in the audience
uh we're both authors on this paper that
we'll be talking today Constructor
Theory as process Theory
um
so
uh well to the format of this discussion
be
so
I'd like to tell you a bit about
constructive theory and process Theory
and then sort of have a discussion about
uh
the the sort of diagrammatics of process
Theory how that might fit with active
inference
um and all this you know you can view it
as an exercise and sort of seeing things
in a diagrammatic way
um so I'll get started and the structure
will be roughly I'll talk about what
Constructor theory is first just from a
conceptual level because I'm the only
non-physicist among the authors of this
paper
hands as a physicist so any questions
about specific examples is there to be
directed to Hamza
uh and then you know after that I'm
going to do just a sort of lightning
fast introduction to what a process
theory is
and then we'll put the two together and
then we'll have a discussion and
throughout I will be making pauses to
sort of invite questions and make sure
everyone is on the same page
conceptually but everything should be
super super easy because I think all the
ideas really are you know fundamentally
they're quite simple
Okay so
without further Ado what is Constructor
Theory
instructor NASA
so you may have heard of this already
because there's quite a lot of hype they
have a they have a very good PR machine
if nothing else
so among other things that's been
described as and I think this is from
quanta article a master Theory a set of
ideas so fundamental that all other
theories would spring from it and in
fact if you go to deutsche's original
paper
on constructive theory he goes so far to
say that all other theories of physics
you know we'll call them you know it
doesn't matter if it's thermodynamics or
Quantum or relativity gravity whatever
we'll just call them subsidiary theories
because that's how big and important
constructive theory is
and uh you know there's this eponymous
book by Kiara maletto the science of
Canon cats
I want to say that oh well you know if
constructive theory is about counter
factuals and what what is and isn't
possible in the domain of physics
um and all this is all this sounds
really impressive but you know the
question is what do you mean by what do
you mean by this so how this is how this
all started is uh some of Kiara's
students anisette and uh Maria villares
they came over
to the Wolfson Quantum foundations
discussion and they were nice enough to
sit down and tell us about what
Constructor Theory really is because you
know historically it's been really
difficult to sort of pin down you know
to pin down like what is
what do you really mean here by all
these words
and uh well
these you know they're happy to say look
you know it's a meta Theory you can sort
of bring your own mathematics you know
what we really there's a sort of
methodological approach of uh
constructive theory that's more
important than the specific mathematics
that you want to use to instantiate all
these words like what is a Constructor
and what is possible and what is
impossible but okay I'll tell you
conceptually what constructive theory is
so first I want I want you to
let's talk about a space of conceivable
processes
conceivable is the word here
the the use of the word conceivable will
become clear soon because
um we're gonna we're gonna cut this
space shortly and what are the sorts of
conceivable processes that we might have
well let's let's look at a limited
subset let's talk about ice cream
a sort of the sort of simple process
that can always happen which is you
might have some ice cream you leave it
up for too long and the ice cream melts
comes a puddle
this is you know we want to say this is
obviously a conceivable process there's
another conceivable process where the
opposite thing happens
you have the ice cream that's melted
and then it spontaneously unmelts and
becomes an ice cream again
this is a conceivable process as well
and then there's a straight up you know
ridiculous stuff that you know we we
know for sure is not going to happen in
the domain it says it's like for example
we have an ice cream and then you've got
some machine such that you can take it
and you can take you put in anything and
it performs it performs this process or
task of taking your input and copying it
everything perfectly down to the down to
the quantum States
you know you're you're cloning the ice
cream and you may be aware of this
Quantum no cloning so we know that this
this sort of thing you know not going to
happen nevertheless all of these are
conceivable processes
um of relationships between possible
inputs and possible outputs I should
stop using the word possible just inputs
and outputs
right so
what is the aim of Constructor Theory
really
well it stems from this desire to
classify the spaces of conceivable
processes into that which is possible
and that which is impossible
well
what might we say intuitively
we might say that well we we're pretty
sure that we're pretty sure that this
this ice cream melting stuff that's
possible in terms of some Theory of
physics that explains everything like
okay fine like some Theory physics that
explains what happens to ice cream we
definitely want to say that ice cream
melting is possible
um and we definitely you know that
Theory of physics also has got to say
that this uh sort of cloning situation
here that's got to be that's got to be
no good that's that's impossible
one of the difficulty comes when you've
got the cases in the Middle where okay
well technically if we're just using
English I mean it is conceivable it is
possible that an ice cream can
spontaneously uh reform itself I mean it
can happen the laws of physics don't
forbid it it is simply very very
unlikely
um what is deutsche's idea that we
should say no no no you know let's do
away with the complexities of statistics
and just say that that's straight up
impossible right
so then the goal of constructive theory
is to take the space of conceivable
processes and cut it
just one cut
corresponding to on one side
what is impossible
and on the other
what is possible
right
so just using this one sort of concept
or Duality what is possible and
impossible it is like you take your
space of conceivable processes and you
just determine what's possible and
impossible and here's the subtle part
then you claim that any Theory of
physics
corresponds precisely to the content of
one of these cuts
and what do I mean by that well
I mean is that well you know here's this
is one space of conceivable processes
that happens to talk about for example
the Dynamics of ice cream
but there are all kinds of conceivable
spaces of processes that might govern
you know different sort of domain or
domains or or magisteria or whatever you
want to call them
of a phenomena
and the idea is that well you know
anytime you have a theory of physics
what do you really have you really have
just a domain of phenomena that you care
about and Constructor Theory says and in
addition to that
a cut that tells you whether
you know what things are possible in
that domain and what things are not
possible
and so then every pair of
you know sort of domain Plus
one of these cuts that tells you what is
possible and impossible
is going to kind of encode or summarize
just be a particular Theory of physics
right
and so we can be very empathetic to this
this uh we can be very empathetic to
this kind of formulation it's a nice
thing to try to do to sort of
uh to summarize or have a sort of bird's
eye view of all these different uh
theories of physics to try to boil it
down to something that's conceptually a
bit simple but of course there are
problems too right so one problem is
well
you know
why didn't you call it a possibility
Theory rather than constructive theory I
don't know the answer to that but
possibility Theory sounds a bit too much
like a mathematical Theory and it
doesn't sound exactly as constructive
theory so that's one reason you might
want to call it a Constructor Theory
but then what is a Constructor what do
Constructors have to do with all of this
this idea of possibility and
impossibility
well you see the difficulty was if you
go back and you think about the case of
the ice cream melting
that's something that is possible
by our usage of the word
but you'd want to be able to stick it on
one side of the cut and call that
impossible right
the solution unfortunately is herbicide
what you do is you simply make up a
technical concept you call this concept
the possible you call this concept
possibility
of a task let's say
and then you well what do you mean by
possibility or task well that relies on
you know defining what these
Constructors are the possibility defines
depends on defining what Constructors
are and Constructors in turn depend on
on the definition of tasks and then
tasks finally are something that you can
cash out in terms of processes
so this is this is the idea of where
constructive theory wants to go
and now I'm going to tell you how it is
that Constructor theorists get there
right
uh let's see do we have
um
do we have any questions at this point
any sort of conceptual questions or
clarifications that anyone wants to
because otherwise I'm gonna
move on
where does likely or unlikely fit that's
all on one side of the line what if
something's vanishingly unlikely
but possible
that is an absolutely brilliant question
um and the answer is
you get to choose as long as you make a
cut because
so the dogma of constructive theory goes
you only get possible and impossible I
don't care how you pick you pick how to
distinguish the likely eventually
unlikely and I didn't make up the rules
I'm merely telling you that everything
has to be either possible or impossible
good question
sorry that's the best that's the best I
can do
um
okay three so
right
what is Constructor Theory all right
it's a
of course it's a meta Theory bring your
own math
the medicine what is that what does that
mean that means bring your own math
okay
let's start from what is a construct
well
you know what
this might be this might be better if I
you know I'm looking at I'm looking at
these notes now and I'm going like nope
I'm gonna
it wouldn't make sense if I started from
there I'm gonna have to put that as the
as the bottom thing and then we'll get
there
what is uh
instructor right
okay let me start with defining what a
task is so all of this so far is going
to be in English and then we're going to
translate to math in a second but hold
on let's let's talk about what a task is
first
from a task you get onto
this remember we we said that something
was conceivable
we have to break down that initial
diagram that we drew this initial
informal thing we we had the sort of the
space of all conceivable task so first
we have to Define what do we mean by
tasks what do we mean by conceivable
tasks
and then from concealable let's just
talk about what do we mean by a possible
task right
and then it will turn out that a
Constructor is a the Constructor is uh
is something that's associated with a
possible task
so that you see that there's a
difficulty here of getting from
Constructors to the you know where
ultimately you want to go there's a sort
of
yeah right logic of justification logic
of Discovery and they don't know
differently okay fine so what is a task
well remember we're allowed to we're
allowed to bring our own mathematics
here so
we we asked them we we took a lot of
care to ask them you know what what sort
of math do you want you know what do you
need here and there and then finally you
know it came down to look look really
what we care about as Constructor
theorists is just defining these things
once you pick some sort of sensible
interpretation of these things in
mathematics then you can go ahead and
play the game of Constructor Theory
so okay that's fantastic you know so so
here we have a here in Oxford we have a
uh we have a nice sort of Homebrew math
what we you know we call them process
theories but otherwise they're known as
symmetrical categories
let me say okay well let's let's call
let's call a task a process
a process
in a symmetric monolithal category
okay well we'll get to what that means
in a second
so what is a conceivable task that
becomes well that becomes mathematically
trivial it just becomes a process inside
a process Theory
well it is a possible task well
possible task is going to be
and then here's where we have to get
technical again what is the possible
task well it's defined as some as an
infinitely iterable task
infinitely iterable yada yada
okay and then if a task turns out to be
one of these infinitely if if a task
turns out to be infinitely iterable we
call it possible and a task always is
doing something and then there's
something in the environment that's
helping it do it that's something in the
environment this super ancillary thing
at the end of these definitions is going
to be what a Constructor is and at this
point it will be very helpful to
actually go through an example and it so
happens that by going through this
example just in the diagrammatic form
you will understand process theories
because the whole point of process
theories and symmetrical categories is
that you have this formal diagrammatic
syntax that's extremely intuitive you
don't have to know anything about the
category Theory you can just use the
diagrams and there's a formal syntax
where you sort of kept all wrong as long
as you're just like composing the boxes
and the wires so
I'm going to now give an example
of
let's make an example of a constructible
and this is also a good time so now that
I'm erasing anytime I'm racing it's a
good time to chime in with questions
sure one question from the chat upcycle
Club wrote does this mean that
Constructor Theory as a process Theory
indeed takes into account the node
deleting theorem
I think
um no no deleting
what do you what do you mean I'm not
familiar with not sure if that's what
was written or maybe you referenced no
cloning earlier I represents no cloning
ah so here's the yeah so here's the nice
bit so earlier I drew a diagram where
there are all these different Blobs of
different colors and each one was a
different uh domain of physics or
whatever right
so it turns out that you know part of
the content of a process Theory or the
symmetric model category is that you
have to pick a category an ambient
category in which you're interpreting
and that choice of ambient category
uh tells you about the sorts that that
is the choice of the conceivable
processes so if you choose the category
of quantum processes and Quantum Maps it
will turn out that in that setting
you have no cloning
but if you pick a different setting like
for example maybe you want just sets and
functions you know mathematical sets and
functions in which case of course you
can copy you can always you know copy
down any information that you have you
know as long as all on paper and you're
just using sets and functions right but
in physics find you we want to model it
with the process theory of uh of quantum
Maps then you don't get you know so it
depends on it depends on the choice of
uh choice of interpreting category but
that's that's a very good conceptual
question thank you
foreign
so
talk about a task I'm going to make a
task here
I'm going to draw these tasks as
directed boxes with wires
um so this is this is just
one of my drawings here okay I've drawn
these directed so because I want
everything to be read from left to right
okay
now in a process Theory every process is
drawn as a box the process is something
that takes as input over here
some systems and does something to it
whatever then it outputs some systems
and then processes can be composed
in you know
a kind of usual way that one expects
this is a composite process for example
all right
so
what is the process so what is the
process here well okay let's let's talk
about uh these systems what I mean by
these systems
can be just about anything it was
subject to a couple of rules the rules
are anytime you have a system you just
need some way
to talk about what it means to have two
of these systems side by side
so let's say that the green system is uh
it's either the green system here so now
this is something that takes in a green
system and
a orange system and gives back the green
system of the orange system
so it's something that's acting on these
systems that returns them
and what I mean by a system or a system
can be it will mathematically we would
call them a type like a system can be
like the booleans or they they can be a
set or they can even have the vector
spaces as systems
and if you have Vector spaces as systems
there are lots of different ways that
you can interpret this idea of sticking
to systems side by side
you can have the direct sum of vector
spaces you have the tensor product and
Vector spaces and all of them will give
you valid process theories so you have
linear maps with direct sum or linear
maps with tensor products and that would
all give you a process Theory or
asymmetrical category in which you can
interpret the diagrams you're drawing
here
so let's let's cut with a simple one
though a simple one is let's say that
this green system is going to be you
know this is terribly drawn oh that's a
slightly better so it's shoes
all right it's a shoe let's say it's a
particular issue right that helps
and what is this other system so what is
this other system I'm going to call this
other system
the system of a bucket with a paintbrush
and Chuck it
and here's a paintbrush
all right
this is perfectly fine systems
talk about these systems can be in
different states
like for example
a shoe can be well it can be clean or it
can be dirty it can have all these
different colors with the bucket well
let's let's talk about buckets you know
sort of having paint inside maybe the
bucket has some paint in that maybe it
doesn't that's a good example of the
system
and I want to model a particular task
here which is Paint The Shoe
right it's a process well another why do
I call it a task well to turn up to to
view a process as a task I have to
I have to look at it in the right way I
have to say like okay well there's got
to be one there's got to be one sort of
system
that's the input and output I want to
call that system the substrate
well why because the task has to you
know that that's the substrate there and
you you know painting has to happen to
something if you want to view painting
as a task in the substrate of the
painting is going to be the shoe
and what about this other what about the
what about the paint
well the paint part okay well that's
going to be part of what we call just
here
everything else that's going to be the
environment
okay
is going to be a substrate an
environment
but then what do we what do we mean by
successfully painting a shoe well
okay so here I'm going to need to
introduce
we need to induce a concept so
green wire is the shoe system
as this orange wire is the bucket and
paint system let's remember that
so now here's the new kind of process
maybe yeah yeah I think about this like
this this is fine
here's a new kind process
so I'm drawing Foster season you've seen
the process at this point that takes
inputs and has outputs
what about a process that doesn't take
any inputs and just gives you an output
well those we call States the special
kind of process
in the process theory of sets and
functions or symmetrical model category
I should say of sets and functions with
Cartesian products states are elements
of sets in the process theory of
relations states are subsets of sets and
systems are sets in uh
in I think any vect whether whether it's
a direct sum or the tensor product a
state is a vector
so States really are just sort of like
some you're really we really call it you
know it's a sort of play on words
because I was saying like oh well you
know the system can have States their
systems can be in different states the
idea is that well actually the name is
well chosen so that a state really is
picking out you know one of the states
of the system that you're interested in
let's say that we'll call there's
there's a sort of state of the shoe
which is that it's unpainted
and there's a state of the bucket and
bucket and paint system
such that you got a bucket that's full
of blue paint
and what do I mean by the task of
painting the shoe
let's see how much is visible oh I've
got all of that all of the side over
here right
now you'll see your first process
theoretic equation
so here's a shoe that's not blue
and here's a bucket of paint
that's now it's got no more blue paint
in it
so what we got here
let's say here
so here's full
right here let's say it's let's say it's
white starts off the white shoe
at the ends
up the painted
I have here
empty
and
this is a process theoretic equation
I hope you can see all the data that's
happening here what we're saying is that
okay look if I've got as initial States
I've got like a I've got an unpainted
shoe and I've got a full bucket of paint
what this process does is it takes the
two systems it views one of them as a it
just keeps track and says okay well this
one's a substrate this one's the
environment
and
what is the result of applying that
process to my two states well then I
have to end up with two new States and
those states are saying well okay now I
end up with a painted shoe and I use up
all my paint so now I haven't I have an
empty can of paint That's not mistake
is that clear because that's that's if
you understand this then you'll
understand everything else I'm about to
say this is maybe the only this is the
only conceptually difficult part on
constructive theory as process Theory
are we happy with this
if anyone's unhappy or has any
conceptual questions and now's the right
now's the right time to ask
it seems like we kind of put a box
around
the entire Crux of the issue but
at this level of abstraction indeed
right indeed right I mean like yeah of
course you uh
there's a lot of there's a lot of boxing
away the Crux of the issue but in fact
we haven't even gotten to rather we
haven't even gotten to the the Crux of
what the Constructor is yet I'm merely
defining what it is for something to be
a task I mean you can then pick so so
the point also of a process theory is
that you can work at the level of
abstraction you so choose think of this
you know if you if you code this is
basically you're declaring what the
types of the the method or the function
are it's still on you to go fill in the
implementation details but here we're
just dealing with the level of this this
is the level of abstraction where it's
it's perfectly okay to start working to
just Define what we mean by a
Constructor and remember that this is
still just an example at some point you
can just erase all the labels and just
keep the coloring that indicates the
types and then that would this would be
the abstract specification of what a
task in a Constructor is
yeah so you're right we are hiding away
a lot of the or hiding away you know the
Crux of the difficulty or the meat but
we're doing so in service of sort of
getting at a formal incarnation of
what's constructive theory is so yeah
um Okay so
kind of happy with this now I'm going to
redo some of this
let's see
so now well let's suppose that it's you
know maybe it's a small bucket of pain
it's a fairly
big shoe in either case the content of
the equation was that you know you stick
in this full bucket of paint and then at
the end of it you run out of paint you
finish painting issue but you run out of
paint
what that means as a sort of
diagrammatic consequence
what happens if we want to paint a shoe
twice
well I mean by that
okay well here
's two shoes and just to distinguish
them I mean uh
just distinguish them let's say that
this one starts off like a
nice yellow shoe and this one's a nice
Orange Shoe
and then in the end we still have this
we have this again this bucket of paint
that is kind of that's full
what do I mean by painting painting Two
Shoes well okay let's let's paint them
in the order that they're closest so
first we want to apply the the paint
shoe task
right we end up with some shoe system we
end up with some bucket of paint system
we want to say okay we'll send that that
first system we send it away that second
system we bring it in
all right now let's line things up again
and let's apply this again
all right
here's the paint shoe and here's you
know let's try it again let's try to
paint the shoe right
and now we've we're seeing a new
diagrammatic component which corresponds
to the word symmetric in a symmetrical
category
the idea is that well in a symmetrical
model category yes you can put systems
side by side but in a sense you don't
care about the spatial configuration of
how you do it you're always free it's
you sort of have a bag of systems you
know to pick them out
and geometrically what this amounts to
in the diagrammatic syntax is saying
that well look if you have a system side
by side you can always you can always
swap the two systems and you can depict
the swaps as uh as wires twisting over
each other
and the sort of the the difficulty of uh
or the only difficult content of the
symmetrical category is showing that you
know the the way that the diagrams
behave topologically correspond
precisely to the algebraic content of of
the the morphisms that are the semantics
of the of the processes which means
which which is to say that as long as
you're tracking the connectivity and the
connectivity matches between two
different diagrams
they're going to refer to the same
formal entity
uh so there is so it's really like a
safe syntax to to use
right but we can follow this right this
is the this is this is what I said I'm
painting I'm trying to paint the two
shoes with one bucket of paint
that should be clear I'm trying to
arrange to paint the first to the orange
shoe
and then I twist in the second yellow
shoe and try to try to apply that
process again to do the painting right
and then remember the diagrammatic
equations the diagrammatic equations Let
Us Reason directly with this um we never
have to sort of leave the diagrams once
we've defined everything
so what do we have well okay the
diagrammatic equation tells us
of what painting shoes does is okay well
this is going to be then the same as
well I empty the bucket of paint
I paint this blue
right
and you'll note that you know it doesn't
matter whether I stretch things it
doesn't matter if I stretch things or I
twist the wires around in a symmetrical
category it you know everything up to
stretching doesn't matter all refers to
the same configuration of states and
applied processes
uh but then I run into a problem here
because okay well
so in a symmetric normal category
everything is okay up to twist so this
thing over here that crosses over
I can sort of pull it I can yank it all
the way
to here
right
and then what do I have well
what is this saying I've just done these
diagrammatic derivations to show that
well I I apply the equation that tells
me that I can use a full can of paint to
paint a shoe
and then I run out of paint and now I'm
trying to apply an empty can of paint to
a shoe that needs to be painted
now this one I'm stuck I have no more
diagrammatic equations to help me you
know get this into a simplified State
from here because well we might want to
define the painting shoe process to be
one such that nothing happens if you put
in the empty
you put in the empty bucket of paint
don't end up painting the shoe okay for
this reason
um
not Constructors yet let us imagine then
that we had this magic bucket of pain
now this is I've cast a spell on it this
is a magic bucket of infinite paint
and the nature of this infinite paint is
that it's always going to be full it's
always going to have enough paint to
paint another shoe
of course such a shoe with such a such a
bucket of paint cannot exist in our
physical reality you guys have to use up
some paint
but if you had this sort of
mathematically ideal infinite bucket of
paint then it doesn't matter how many
shoes you try to paint you could always
then sort of apply another equation and
then you go like well you know the empty
bucket of the paint is not going to run
out so I can I can apply the equation
again and I can paint another shoe and I
can keep painting shoes and every time I
apply the equation well it never goes
from a full state to an empty state it
just stays in the same infinite state
and it allows me to perform this task
again and again and again however many
times I want
rather counter-intuitively this is what
is meant by possible
so painting a shoe as I've described it
using just a regular bucket of paint
that empties is actually not a possible
task
in the framework of constructive theory
right this is what I mean by herbicides
you know you'd want to say of course you
can paint a shoe no no no no
possibility is a completely political
term that refers to the ability of a
task to be iterated infinitely
and then this thing this infinite bucket
of paint here this state that enables
the task the environmental state that
enables the task to be repeated
infinitely which is to say after you
apply the task once the resulting
transformation on the environment leaves
it in such a state that it can do the
task again
nothing is a Constructor
okay
so
I'm gonna move on to what's next uh what
is next what is next but this is a good
time to ask questions this is a very
good time to ask questions
do you want to ask a question
no I don't have any questions
okay
um
well why well
I suppose uh what else can I say about
Constructors here well conceptually
where do instructors come from
if you think about uh you know catalysts
or some biological reactions the
catalyst is the the notion of a catalyst
in chemistry and biochemistry this is
this is one of the sort of
yeah
the sort of intellectual sources of this
idea of a Constructor you know if you
replace Constructor with Catalyst it
doesn't really change much about how you
should Intuit the thing
it's this idea that well you know you
need it in order to help this help this
uh transformation occur but then at the
end you just get the Catalyst back and
then the catalyst is unchanged and you
can go and participate in another
participate in another reaction
right so so that's
this is the sort of idea of like what a
Constructor is
um okay so why again is uh
what should I talk about here
we can talk about okay we still have to
get to this idea of the cut so how is
how is it that this how is it that these
uh having this notion now of a
Constructor helps us Define what we mean
by a cut yeah that's it
cut if possible and not possible okay
so what is a Constructor
okay
let's I'm going to rehearse one more
time this uh I'm going to simplify it
uh what I want to do here yeah okay
and I have now this
this infinite bucket of paint
right
and I have all the shoes I'll get to in
a second
so
for whatever reason
constructive theorists really like to
use the category of sets and relations
they really like to think of things in
terms of sets and relations
which is a problem when you're trying to
model Quantum things and we can get into
that in a second
um how did this come about well you know
the usual way which is to say when David
Deutsch wrote his first paper he said
well you know let's just you know let's
take certain relations as this sort of
setting where we can start doing some
calculations and we'll use it as a
placeholder setting for now and of
course you know no one no one bothers to
ever go back and change the placeholder
than it then the placeholder becomes a
standard so okay fine they use they use
sets and relations
and then so the the systems in the
process Theory we'd call them systems
but in the
uh constructive theory we would call
them substrates or the environments no
there's going to be sets they're going
to be sets of going to be sets of
and again we're dying under the
terminology here
sets of macro States finally we want
let's just talk about macro States well
okay I mean like this is a this is a
deep Constructor Theory lore thing
because they need to just they need to
talk about like thermodynamics in a
second
um
so why macro States because there's lots
of different ways a shoe can be blue you
know if you're really looking at it at
the at the molecular level you know
there's all these different
configurations and you know you kind of
don't care and you want to say like well
look all of them just count as blue as
far as I'm concerned we'll call all of
that
we'll call all of that the the macro
States of
the the shoe being blue
and then there's shoe being whatever
other color and you don't really care
um
and then the job of this task
drop of this task here
is just to take
the macro states that are not blue and
to turn them into macro states that are
blue
and it must be so for
well it doesn't matter if this is a set
that's going to be a set of
microstates macro States turns out
doesn't matter when you're working
process theoretically we show in the
paper that like look there is this uh
there is this distinction at the
mathematical level when constructed
theorists talk about this between like a
particular molecular configuration and
the macro states of a collection a
sub-collection of configurations that
are blue or whatever
but you know what we show is like look
look in this system it doesn't matter
you can just work directly with the
macro States because that would that's
what you really want and it turns out
mathematically it doesn't make a
difference
so what are we saying a Constructor is
here's a definition of a Constructor
we're saying that
this equation all to hold
right what I mean by this I mean by this
fill in the language of uh in the
diagrammatic language for sets and
relations you've got a special State and
you've got a special something that's
the co-state or an effect something that
only takes inputs and doesn't give you
any outputs
what's this special state
remember states in the symmetric model
category of relations satellite
relations are subsets and this special
state is the special subset of
everything in the so what this part the
diagram says here
just up to here saying okay well look
here's my Constructor
that's in my environment and my
substrate is well okay I don't care what
you put in here it could be any macro
state
but you perform this task
and then the opposite of
give me everything well here is the
effect the relation that is the converse
of this this uh well something that
takes every
uh it's something that takes every
element of a set to the signal Singleton
so it's
it's the equivalent of deleting or
forgetting about it
and in total what this is saying here
look if you apply this if you apply this
process view it as a task
it takes this Constructor
in the environment acting on a substrate
now look if you if you forget about it
marginalize over or you just Trace out
or whatever words you want to use to say
just forget about it it doesn't matter
what you put in in the substrate
you're going to get back
something that is good to go again as a
Constructor and now rather than equality
because of working in sets and relations
and recall that these states are now
subsets
we'd say well look if I give you
if I give you a Constructor what I what
I mean to give you here is a sub I'm
going to give you
a a set or a collection of macro states
that all work as
Constructors
um because of course the infinite bucket
of paint might also have Micro States
you know the paint could be in different
configurations but they might all be
equally infinite and good for the pro
good for this task but I give you all of
these and
if you apply the if you apply the
process to it and you do the task you
get back
you get back a set of states that is
good to go again as uh to to run this
you can just plug that into another copy
of this equation and you can just get it
again and again
this is now
minus the
now we can just take away all of the
sort of stuff that's still tethering us
to intuition
and at that point that is just the
definition of a constructive
right this is that that's a construction
yeah
okay
so what can we do uh
what can we do with uh Constructors so
Recall now this is
this is going to be the Constructor and
this is by virtu a task which by virtue
of having a Constructor that's going to
be a possible task
right
possible task
and now
final bit that we need to get to to end
the this conceptual story of what's
going on in the paper and we can move on
to a discussion
is uh
well what it what do we mean by this cut
remember there was this cut between you
know so those all these conceivable
tasks and then there was a cut then you
had all these possible tasks and then
all these impossible tasks how do you
get that cut again
well
you know you have a sub-process theory
so process Theory
process theory is closed under
composition in two ways you can compose
processes and sequence and you can
compose processes in parallel
process Theory says well you give me a
bunch of processes and the processors
well I'll give you the closure all the
conceivability is the closure of these
processes under sequential and parallel
composition
and just you know what I mean by a
sub-process theory well
in the same way that you can have a
subgroup or you can have a uh you can
have a vector space that embeds into
another you know a sub something of some
other mathematical construct we're
saying well you can also have another
process Theory where you start off with
a subset of processes and then you take
the closure of that
under sequential and parallel
composition
and twists in the case of the symmetric
model category
and then you end up with well that's
also a process Theory and it can be a
process Theory that's a subset of a
larger process Theory
and so translating all of that into so
so translating the sort of mathematics
there into sort of touching the
Constructor Theory we'd be saying that
look what we would have to show
in order to claim that you know this
definition is somehow good for where
constructive theory uh construct a
theorists want to go is we want to say
that the possible tasks themselves form
a process Theory
the possible tasks you know what do I
mean by that well that means just that
you know if I give you or identify where
the possible tasks are which tasks are
possible
in an ambient process Theory
then these possible tasks with
Constructors
form a
sub symmetric mineral category which is
to say
the
sequential or parallel composition of
possible tasks again yields a possible
task
right
and that is not too difficult to show
that is not too difficult to show and
perhaps like you can
you know this is the sort of thing that
you can this is the sort of thing that
you can try at home if you have
if you have the pen and paper follow
along
all I have to do well once you have this
equation I mean all you have to do is
check you know because this is this
sorry this in equation this substitute
relation must be verified to define
whether a task is possible this this
inequality simultaneously defines
possible tasks and Constructors so uh
that has to be verified for every
sequential composite that you can come
up with and every parallel composite
that you can come up with and that's not
so bad I'll show you show you one maybe
um again questions welcome
is the mind a Constructor
is the Mind constructed yeah well that
depends on your
depends on what you mean it depends on
depends on the the the process Theory or
this or whatever other mathematical
Incarnation you pick for the
constructive theory remember it's a meta
Theory you bring your own mathematics so
I can't answer that question until the
mathematics is brought and they're you
know all the English has been turned
into math and then I can say oh yes
that's a short or no
so it depends
that's pretty good
I like that
okay what is the
okay here let's say I have you have two
tasks I'm not a fan of using letters I'm
more of a fan of using colors but if
anyone is uh if anyone is colorblind or
if anything's not clearer then just let
me know
maybe there's a different yep
that's
then just to make sure everything
matches up to this end
okay
so here is how here is how we're going
to sequentially compose tasks
right uh
this here is the task
uh task one task two both tasks they
work on the same substrate so for
example paint issue and then unpaint
issue sequential composition of tasks
well if you're going to sequentially
compose it needs to be on the same
substrate otherwise sequential
composition that's meaningless and you
might want something like parallel
composition instead
so for example you can compose the tasks
which may not be possible tasks so paint
the shoe and then strip the shoe of
paint I don't like it you know do
something else with it
um and here's how we'll sequentially
compose just conceivable tasks if you
have a conceivable task that's operating
on this orange substrate you need to
compose something else that takes
oranges that substrate again
but what about the environment the
environment can differ like for example
if I'm going to paint a shoe with paints
versus if I'm going to I don't know do
one of those elect electrolysis chrome
dipping of a shoe to get it covered in
Chrome the environment is going to be
different right so for the first task I
have this particular
well the first task I have this
particular environment
the second task that has its own
those environments are just systems like
say that well okay if I'm going to
sequentially compose I feed in the
requisite environment to do task number
one
and then I twist in and feed in the
requisite environment to do task number
two
and then just to make sure that
everything type checks at the end
this entire thing here
right
now maybe it's better if I
like gather these guys here to make it
clear
all right that's sequential composition
what does it saying
right you can always gather
systems can also be composite systems
that are placed next to each other
this entire thing says well you've got
to give me the environments for the two
different tasks and the substrate
then I'll give you back the environments
again for the two different tasks and
the substrate
that's how we achieve the sequential
composition of tasks so these two small
tasks
put them together just like this and
then you get this one big task
right
what about parallel composition
parallel composition looks
really similar
the parallel composition you can compose
whatever doesn't really
uh apparently composition doesn't
particularly matter
if I get this right here so
we got substrate one yeah or an orange
we got substrate two over here
I'm gonna do it like this that makes it
easier than that
I got environment one
and then environment two
and then
those are your two tasks
and this is your composite test
is that all visible from there
I wonder
hopefully that's kind of a difference
yeah fantastic
um
so again what are we saying well we've
got if you want a parallel compose
parallel composition of task is
fantastic you don't need to match up
with the substrate you can
simultaneously on one side paint shoes
and the other one go you know do your
taxes or whatever it is is another task
whatever
so you can have two completely different
substrates doesn't particularly matter
you have two different environments for
those substrates in that particular task
and here's the parallel composition of
conceivable tasks
you know same principle if you
understand sequential composition and uh
you're happy it's just intuiting the
twisting wires then you're good
and now to verify that
these guys are
so now that to verify that the
composition of possible tasks is again
a possible task
s now let's say that these guys are
possible tasks in other words
that there is a particular
instructor
or green
and there's a particular Constructor
for yellow over here
right
and remember to check the condition
and just delete those right
so how do we go about verifying this
well
what we want to do is we want to apply
the screen one here first we probably
want some kind of formal condition on
our tasks on our possible tasks to tell
us that
this goes through
to then get us
that we have this series
of inequalities I'm winging it here but
there's going to be a proper worked out
version
you know the longer version of this
paper
through
that goes in I'm happy to take questions
as well and longest over here
messing around
and then apply it again
right
I think in the paper we do like one of
these Renovations it's so hard
the principle is kind of simple you
apply the equation that's uh sorry the
end the the containment relationship
that defines possibility on uh on both
of these one by one
and you also make use of the fact that
well there's a special state that one
that corresponds to everything and
delete
pull those through as well for tasks
then you end up with this and then you
go okay fine I verified that
this is uh verified that this is a
possible task and then you do the same
for parallel composition
and then you're done then you say okay
well if I I know that if I sequential
and parallel composition
Plus checking the twists okay that then
I have another process Theory which
means that my possible tasks form
a a process Theory so what do I have I
get to say
I get to finally give
you know
mathematically formal voice so
what a constructive theorist might want
to do
so again
I have
this first
I mean here what is that that is going
to be
this space of conceivable tasks
that's going to be some symmetric
monitorial category
just telling me this is the domain in
which I'm interpreting a particular
process Theory
and these in this symmetric nodal
category well my conceivable tasks they
can compose and sequence and in parallel
what I mean by the cuts or the cuts that
distinguishes what is possible for
impossible
well it turns out that the possible
stuff
that is also a symmetric monitorial
category and that's a symmetric group
minority category that embeds
into the larger one it embeds in the
same way that a subgroup embeds it
embeds in the same way that
um a sub a vector Subspace or linear
Subspace is going to embed into a larger
one
and then everything else well then
everything else is going to be well you
know no promises this is not the sort of
stuff this is you know impossible stuff
is the stuff that doesn't necessarily
iterate instantly because they don't
have Constructors
and
and if you followed along so far
and there's more details in the paper
for if you want to like look up formal
details
uh you understand now Constructor Theory
minus
principle of locality
which
perhaps not interesting enough to Merit
uh further comment but um if someone's
curious about it we can talk about it
uh but you know so what I presented so
far
um is you know a constructive theorists
would also be happy to say yes this is
constructive theory
minus principle of locality so you don't
go around you know saying that this
thing is just constructive theory to a
constructive theorist because they'll
get mad at you and they'll say no no
it's missing the principle of locality
but that's a dogma and you don't you
don't particularly need it like that's
it messes a lot of things up
okay so that's that's all I have to say
for now I think and uh
yeah happy to take it to a discussion
now
awesome wow
um Muhammad would you like to give a
first comment or reflection or just
share what what angle you participated
in the work from
yeah I am interested in applying this
formalism to uh the various examples
that constructive theory has been
applied to so you might have seen papers
by
constructed theory of information and
constructive theory of life
and I'm also interested in seeing how it
applies to quantum theory
and if the process view can be shown to
be uh superior to the constructed
theoretic field
cool so
if you have a given system of Interest
like let's just say a cognitive system
like a person or an aunt or something
like that like how do you go about
demarcating what
tasks are in play are these cognitive
tasks
or are these the tasks that the body
performs
how do we begin to to analyze a
situation in a way that's amenable to to
Being Framed like this
um
so but like this could you could you
refine the uh the discourse preference
what do you mean by this yeah if if we
want to understand if we want to
understand
a given informal actual embodied system
in a way that's amenable to all of the
compositional Bountiful benefits
what are we actually looking to break
down about that system of Interest
sure
um
[Music]
so
when we talked about so tasks are kind
of kind of this ad hoc thing right
is remember that when we do tasks we
drew them like directed in this way
because we had to say something about
production and then we distinguished
between their substrates and their
environments and then we said that uh
systems are always these things which
sort of have there you're sorry the task
is something that takes in the system
and the environment and returns to the
same system and environment which is
which is something that you you can just
accept but also
you know in general a process doesn't
need to have the same inputs and output
types so this is this is perfectly fine
as well you can have a process that's
hit like that and maybe for some sorts
of you know at the whatever level of
abstraction you care about
um it might be more well there's maybe
there's level abstraction where you
don't care about the actual physics of
what's going on where everything is sort
of like conservative on some level
you might just care about a view of the
system where you have inputs and output
types in which case
the language of or the the framework of
thinking about tasks is
uh perhaps less fundamental I mean one
of the points that we're making here is
like the framework of thinking and task
is a task is a constructed concept on
top of the more fundamentally primitive
notion of just being able to construct
processes right and and or just being
able to compose
processes so then it would depend now on
on what you sort of want from
um your notion of task
so what what we were able to show is
that look just using the language of
process Theory we were able to code and
formalize this particular notion of what
we want tasks to behave like
but then depending on what you would
consider a task to be maybe the same
maybe different
um you can encode it in this in this
mathematical language
and then start reasoning about it in a
diagrammatic way
and there's a lot of things you can
reason about in process theoretic
there's a there's a thought there's a
laundry listed button on the paper like
electrical circuit Theory quantum theory
most notably
um the neural algebra first order logic
yeah it's all good
um
maybe that's maybe that's not quite a
satisfactory direct answer but perhaps
we can refine the question and the
target
so to add to add to it uh it's up to
it's up to the modeler or the user to
the site which processes are to be
modeled so you can I mean if you want to
if you want to think about cognitive
processes then you are you know you can
theater
sub-symmetrical category to work with
that but you can also have
a more mechanical process theories or
you can even have one where both
mechanical and cognitive processes
interact so it's up to the model I would
say there's no hard and fast rule in the
formalism
it's the shoe painting Factory
[Music]
um but
a lot a lot to say on that
um inactive inference we're often
interested in a general cybernetic
entity or thing something that's
engaging in sense making on the inbound
and on action selection decision making
on the outbound and
another important idea from ecological
psychology is this notion of like
extended cognition and the environment
and the interactions of the agent
environment so
I wondered is the substrate you were
twisting different environments in
and keeping the spotlight on the thing
it is that how you track an entity
as things change around it
is by twisting in and out different
contexts or
right
um so that's
um
that is just the way for that is just a
way to define
a
it's a fine to Define uh the sequential
composition or the parallel composition
of tasks
in a way that relies upon a more
primitive notion of the sequential and
parallel composition of processes
so
the twisting in and keeping a spotlight
on a particular context so so one of the
things that so one of the things that
we've seen
um that you we've all seen in this in
these examples
is that uh you can start with a process
theory of like basic processes that just
compose in sequence and in parallel and
then you can define a new way to compose
in sequence and in parallel on top of
that
and that would give you a new symmetric
model category that would give you a new
process Theory
so
so you can cut yeah this is so this is a
process Theory kind of there's a dog
food thing here somewhere where you're
kind of eating your own dog food right
um in the case of the the twisting which
was what was the twisting again
here's the twist thing we were saying
that okay well look we're going to
Define instead of just plugging things
together we're going to define a new
kind of uh
we're going to find a new kind of
sequential composition that looks like
this
where instead of just taking two boxes
and joining them together
we do all this other we do all this
other business over here like this is
this is this other business over here
right
um
that's
allowed and good and expressive
but that's also something that the
mathematics has no stance on like if you
so you you brought in these Concepts
like this is how you're spotlighting a
particular substrate and keep and
switching out the context right and if
you look at the diagram it's perfectly
okay to start pointing at these things
saying well of course you're
spotlighting the substrate and you're
switching out the contexts but that's on
you
that's on you the mathematics just just
tells you like this is a way to compose
in sequence
um but it does so nicely enough in a way
that's
you know where where this sorts of uh
the sort of we can we can bring our
linguistic intuitions to bear on the
situation in a much more direct way
because we have the visuality of it
available to us
yeah
that's very deep the necessary and
sufficient
conveyance is on the Blackboard and then
that enables us to take perspectives and
direct attention and have procedural
flows with our attention and tell
narratives and and again have
interpretations
but the interpretation isn't what's
written on the screen
yes
all right a question from the live chat
can you please explain in what way does
that cut
I believe between the possible and
impossible allow the modeler to express
immersion phenomena or laws that arise
from the underlying processes in
Constructor Theory
important processes and laws that arise
from the underlying
in what ways does the cut allow the
modeler to express emergent phenomena or
laws that arise from the underlying
processes
yeah well
um if I could just ask for clarification
from live chat here
and maybe happens I can weigh in as well
but like what's your well what's a
what's your favorite toy example of the
emergence I'm not a constructive
theorist but you know we can play with
the system and we can play with the
system live and see what we we get at
but first we're gonna you know what are
you thinking in terms of immersions
people mean different things sometimes
when they say that right
about the the arising directionality of
a flock of birds
the arising directionality of a flock of
birds
um
oh as in there's a dynamic system that's
evolving over time which is you've got
these birds that are interacting with
each other locally and then they and
then they end up
yes
with these so I think the safe answer or
my intuition would say that the vast
majority of things you would consider to
be possible are
not actually technically possible in
Constructor Theory right
so right off the bat you can say look
you've got this intuition so so if you
thought painting shoes was a fine
sensible thing
and you think that birds flying around
and interacting with each other is a
fine sensible thing that's possible that
probably isn't what is meant by possible
so so in the case of like a in the case
of like a bird system you've got this
massive interacting system fine a
Constructor
a cons you know you probably could have
like a sort of infinite shotgun
Constructor that just stops all the
birds dead in their tracks
again and again and you can you can kill
as many birds as you want
a little construct it for this sort of
system be well if you can set up a
if you can set up an environment that
sort of steers the birds a possible task
maybe for a chaotic system the only
possible task is the trivial one where
you don't expect anything to be done and
you accept any sort of outcome
uh but if you want the particular
possible task that's tantamount to
programming like a flock of birds
or finding some way to program a thought
flock of birds like a deterministic and
set way that you can keep doing it again
and again right
yeah
so so what is the relationship between
Constructor Theory and programming
um there's that's a pretty good question
um I'm going to try my best to answer on
behalf of constructive theorists here
um but there there's this uh
there's a sort of there's an information
Theory or a person or or perspective on
information theory that also comes about
from constructive theory
so as a
as a math and computer scientist myself
I'd say that perhaps the most
fundamental
uh point of contact between constructive
theory and programming is in a notion of
information
and what in particular you're allowed to
do with it
so in a Quantum setting you cannot clone
information your information is carried
in your qubits and you have no cloning
so you can't you can't clone information
um whereas and everything's not
everything that's not classical you know
the technical terms say well
everything's not Quantum you call it
classical in the classical setting you
can copy information you can write down
a one or a zero on a piece of paper and
you can get something to copy them but
one and zero as many times as you want
you can stick the ones and zeros into
filing cabinets so and by so doing
perform computation with copying
let's look at the difference there is
well okay if you've got different sort
of underlying capacities for copying
things and not being able to copy things
in your underlying process Theory
um
what is uh
I guess the sorts of there's questions
asked about the sorts of programs you
can write but that's kind of
kind of a at a much more fundamental
level I mean Constructor Theory
if you if you gave me a if you gave a
particular process theory of programs
then we can start talking constructive
theory
um Constructor theorists so I think by
and large are more interested in the
physics which is at a much lower and
more basic level of abstraction so I I
don't know when you're so when you're
asking about like is this you know is
this a get rich quick scheme when it
comes to emergence is this a get rich
quick scheme when it comes to you know
programming and understanding chaotic
Behavior etc etc you know sorry but the
answer is no like there's there's
nothing the extent I mean if you can
unders you understood the content of
constructive theory in about like an
hour and it was all the pictures like
there's nothing more complicated than
that everything else beyond that is you
hallucinating interpretations onto the
pictures it's a get epistemically rich
quick scheme
good episode
yeah yeah yeah yeah get epistemically
rich quick you know you've got the
pictures and they're very suggestive but
you know in principle it's no different
from like uh a tarot reading you've got
just a very suggestive of mathematics
and and you can read whatever meanings
that in you want and you can play with
the mathematics you can also get some
meanings out but you know you only get
it out as much as you put in in terms of
like uh epistemically weight-bearing
interpretations of hallucinations in the
first place right well it's an
interesting date with Constructor Theory
and process Theory and active inference
none of which are opinionated in The
Last Mile about any given system but all
of which
are providing us higher levels of
expressivity
and increasingly inactive inference
category theory is being used to
represent the kinds of generative models
that are used and so there's the math
and the analytical equations and then
there's the kinds of Bayesian graphs
that we've traditionally looked at the
partially observable Markov decision
processes and then in the last years
there's some
string diagrams and all these other
features coming in that are helping like
expand the scope
of What kinds of cognitive models and
the relationships between
substrates and cognitive processes that
we want to explore
indeed I I I'm familiar with the
friends with Toby Toby Sinclair Smythe
and uh yeah that's that's my only
contact to active inference but I can I
can definitely see the um the appeal of
having a
um
the the appeal of having non-opinionated
mathematics for for things that in the
last mile as you say
don't have an opinion and but but you
know I'm saying I'm butchering it I'm
tired and I'm saying it all wrong but
I'm saying that look I think it's a good
idea to have like a map of composition
to deal with a complex system that's
fundamentally compositional
yeah
um so what do we what modules do we load
in or what do we bring in in our
environment
to be able to to load up and actually
use
so he said bring your own math that was
right at the beginning so it's like okay
what do I bring pianos axioms or what do
I bring like my f of x or what I mean by
the mathematics that has to be brought
okay
um
so when it comes so so the the sort of a
basic uh
the the the core module that you sort of
get with process theories
is a theory of composition that works
for
uh anything that you can name processes
that act on systems and these processes
can compose in sequence and in parallel
this is the this is the sort of basic
conceptual map that you get and becomes
gun to head formal
when you load it into a process Theory
that's that's what you get that's core
and then
everything else uh
is actually expressed like sort of in
terms of the
in terms of the diagram so for example
this piano's axioms right
um
let's talk about the
what is it nice
I forget what the axioms are but I know
that there are two generators you've got
a zero
you got a zero State and then you've got
a successor box
right and maybe the first thing that you
want to do if you want to actually well
you want to load in
um anything that you can express at the
end of the day in terms of algebra and
symbols and equations
is also doable
um
with also doable like diagrammatically
like for example I believe that in the
piano formulation the addition operation
is something that's sort of uh
that behaves like a homomorphism with
respect to
or like a module with respect to the
successor box so something like
um
something like this is right
yeah
the axioms are proto-procedural
in that they Define exactly what can and
can't be done
indeed indeed so the the sort of
benefits of thinking in a or let's say
depicting in a process theoretic way is
that well look if you're more used to
talking about processes and how they
interact and you you don't really care
you don't want to you know spell out
from the bottom up how they're
implemented and do a sort of calculation
with like the specifics what you really
just care about or the operational
constraints of how they compose and
behave when you compose them together
and you can express them in terms of
equations or containment relations or
whatever else
then the process theory is much better
as opposed to for example just dealings
with the sets you know the you know
especially if you've got like a very
complex system then you know no hope
again to these two key features of
cognitive systems like the sense making
on the inbound and the the associated
World model and then the action
selection I've I thought about the first
blob you drew with the conceivable
that's like well you drew the lines we
have the rest of the Blackboard so it's
like we know that there's unconceivable
but that's that's the scope of the sense
making for a given setting and then the
the line between what is possible and
what isn't possible is is what is
actionable
and
I guess you can develop thought settings
where okay well I'm gonna
um speculate what could happen if I
could lift up ten thousand pounds and
then you could do tasks related to
moving cargo containers whereas if you
um were using tweezers and you defined
what was possible with with a different
threshold then there'd be different
kinds of plausible tasks
and yeah so
yeah so for
the sort of
what what might interest you is well I'm
going to Shield it now why not I've got
some time
my interest to you for this sort of
reading is that well for Constructor
Theory you know it really just wants to
force you on one side of a binary and
this may be too restrictive ex you know
in terms of expressive capacity when
you're trying to especially map it onto
something that involves anything as
complex as the distinction between
cognitive and physical tasks and
processes right and and we had questions
to this uh to this effect earlier as
well like what do we do with the likely
what do we do with the vanishingly
unlikely what do we do with the
plausible right how do we so I want to
point out that and this is something
that's coming in the longer version of
the paper is uh
is a relationship between
um uh constructive Constructor Theory as
a special case of resource theories so
you know this idea that you have to with
the constructive theory you have to
either go like infinitely many times or
you know infinite or bust
a resource theory is sort of going like
yeah but you know we'd be happy also if
we could do it a couple of times you
know tell me how many times you can do
it you know that's pretty good and so
you know resource Theory and principle
give you this idea of like well you know
here's the sort of things that you can
do once you can do twice that you can do
three times you can do
and finally
you know in the in the very very core
over here
you know that's the sort of stuff that's
picked out
that's the sort of stuff that can be
picked out by a constructive theoretic
Cuts in the limit
whereas a resource theoretic point of
view is saying like well of course you
know you if you want to make more
distinctions than that then like an easy
generalization that's also quite simple
to think about is let's talk about the
stuff that we can do for free all the
time let's talk about the things that we
only you know we only get to do once
um and it turns out that resource
theories are particularly
you know resource theories are actually
like a practical bit of mathematics when
it comes to uh
Quantum circuit optimization because
there are certain components that are
very expensive and you want to be able
to work out what sort of quantum maps
you can implement
only using this particular sat gate
let's say like three times or maybe you
get like one extra one or maybe you get
like two less and then you know the
resource theory is going to tell you
precisely you know what your gain and
loss and expressive capacity is when you
have more few fewer or more resources
which is something that is a very
computer sciencey down to earth
practical thing as opposed to just the
distinction between infinity and and
everything else
The Constructor Theory gives you but
sneak peek for for someone that's coming
the next to the next installment or the
extended version of this paper that's
going on archive
that is super exciting and relevant
certainly
organizations or any other kind of
system that's being designed and having
an ability to handle the finite
um very relevant here's one other kind
of speculative question so of course we
had the ice cream belting and unmelting
yeah yeah yeah yeah you had the ice
cream
um on melting as impossible yeah but of
course yeah yeah in a freezer in a
freezer it does happen and or at room
temperature with a reverse time Arrow
and so yeah within this notion of the um
Gibbs free energy we have catalysts like
protein enzymes which are not able to
enable what isn't possible but rather
they can accelerate by reducing the
activation energy and they can
accelerate a negative Delta G and they
can accelerate something that is
possible catalytically hence Catalyst
and be regenerated right and it made me
think about the change in variational
free energy as the ball rolling downhill
cognitively and about how the the
channels and the Landscapes of the mind
or of the cognitive system
um sometimes
the landscape is changed and what is
possible becomes different but just
because something's possible doesn't
mean it's ever reached and then we still
need this question of the catalyst
to actually Implement and get it to
where it can be
right right
and and I I think that perhaps one of
the
one of the sort of intuitive appeals of
Constructor theory is that you know at
first glance and with an intuitive
mapping of Concepts
this sound Constructor Theory sounds
like the right kind of mathematics to
talk about you know these these
interactive Concepts that you're talking
about the free energy and catalysis as
enabling
but the caveat with constructive theory
remember is infinite robust hard
binaries
which means that if you want to do so
like I'm sorry to say but if you want to
do anything that's remotely nuanced more
nuanced than like
a pair of qubits interacting which
already because of principal locality
gives Constructor theorists a lot of
pain
because soccer theory is probably not
the right system for you
process theories though if you want to
deal with composition not bad especially
you know you gotta you get diagrams for
free and also you get other add-ons that
are very good at doing the sort of
things that you want to do
let's have the right expressivity and
shape like resource theories Constructor
Theory one should think of as a
particular way or methodology
uh that's designed for a particular
problem to be a meta Theory of physics
in in whatever David in whatever David
Deutsch considers to be like a sort of
conceptually clean setting of just being
able to make a single cut to tell you
about like to distinguish in a black and
white way all of all the physics
interesting and in the Bayesian
mechanics
which is some of the recent developments
in active inference and free energy
principle area that yeah grounding of
physics
to I guess what we want to call physical
even though we know that so many
asterisks have to be added when we knock
on the wood and everything like that but
if the physics of cognitive systems can
be described purely informationally
then we can have a procedural
compositional cognitive physics that
would enable us to do anything from
the mind conceptualizing that the shoe
could be a different color to the
multi-agent setting and composed across
individuals and
there's just
there's there's more walls to paint on
well there are many possible walls to
paint on
yes
um yeah I'm
what are you curious about her I mean
what what's an exciting Direction
foreign
in terms of uh in terms of what exactly
because in terms of uh
this whole business with constructive
theory this is kind of a side project
for me
a fun one but just
the side interest
um what's your what's your main interest
or what what motivates or what excites
the context such that this could be a
side interest
um
well uh you know my main interest is
more uh
I suppose it's more aligned with this
notion of sense making
um my
my interest is sort of using diagrams
not only for sense making but as a
formal uh platform to you know
articulate
theories of what since making one might
be so I played around with so these
diagrams that you know they're good for
Quantum for example but the same kind of
mathematics
is quite good for other sorts of
positive you know there are other
domains not just for example psychology
that are you know
dearly in need of some sort of
compositionally native approach like
diagrams like Linguistics for example
um so
I like to draw language and because
language is a particular tool of sense
making and then to formalize the the
kind of sense making that we make for
example when we
no we use we use metaphor to like to get
the point across relies on a complex
metaphor where information is stuck into
words as a box and then the boxes moved
across a conduit and this sort of sense
making
um is beyond the merely let's say truth
theoretic
uh yet nevertheless is systematic in a
way such that the compositional aspects
of the language precisely map onto the
compositional aspects of the domain of
sense making
um and I suspect that's where we might
have more to talk about
um because you know sense making is I
consider sense making it's a it's you
know capital S very
it's a it's a very big thing and perhaps
like the important activity to
understand
um
and I'm interested in the systematicity
of it and in particular trying to depict
that's systematicity that's something
yeah there's something that's you know
direct about the about string diagrams
in the same way that perfume or music is
sort of directed it's not mediated by
the
you know by the by the rows of Greek and
the symbols right
so I don't know maybe maybe that's uh
yeah
wow there's a lot there can we say that
the the screen
is the substrate that we're writing
language on if we're going by hand with
pen
and then we have an infinite pen
and this is this is the inexhaustible
pen
and then
that certainly does seem to be one thing
at which the yeah yeah yeah I mean you
mean to refer to in the context of the
mind we have a I mean as long as we're
not a fantasic we have a sort of theater
of mind that's sort of infinitely
refreshable paper or infinitely
refreshable uh
stage for us to arrange things on and
and and sort of replenish the
representation
that's
that does sound kind of like a
Constructor
if we're if we're happy also to sort of
uh
sort of rule out heraclitus or
heraclitus you mentioned hurricane was
earlier you know a man never steps to
the same river twice you know are we
insofar as we are the same entity that
is perhaps
observing the theater of Mind as we're
infinitely refreshing it then fine yeah
it's a Constructor but
is it the same if if you know 10 years
on you're you're a functionally
different person is that still uh
is it is it still the same task
is it still the same task refreshing or
looking at a memory 10 years on
I don't know
the I
is able to to Nest sub tasks
however it may not have the awareness to
know what it is
embedded within but at least within this
internal theater
it can make a sub
representation that it believes could be
wrong but that it believes would have
continuity also Beyond itself
but also not saying what is beyond
itself
Beyond itself in in what sense
um
like there's the environments that
one is confronted with and then one
could at least suspect that there are
other environments that one is not being
confronted with but also know that they
can't say anything more than that about
environments that they aren't being
confronted with
yes I
I'm not sure what to say to that but
I'll have to think about that once
before we have to go
um well I'm I'm very good
um just I'd like to everyone to know
that the
longer version of this very paper is uh
going to come out soon ish on archive
where
uh we work out some more examples we
relate to constructive theory to
Resource theories and everything is
going to be very readable so if this
condensed Journal version is a bit
Technical and difficult to follow watch
the space and there's going to be a
uh longer and more pedestrian version
that hopefully everyone can follow
yeah
yeah great
thank you both for joining hope to um
see you again it's a very exciting and
evocative line of work
thank you thanks Daniel hope to see you
again soon farewell bye bye